you
Krishnamurti in dialogue with Dr. Alan
W. Anderson. J. Krishnamurti was born in
South India and educated in England. For
the past 40 years he has been speaking
in the United States, Europe, India,
Australia, and other parts of the world.
From the outset of his life's
work he repudiated all connections with
organized religions and ideologies and said that
his only concern was to set men
absolutely unconditionally free. He is the
author of many books, among them the
Awakening of Intelligence, The Urgency of
Change, Freedom from the Known, and The
Flight of the Eagle. This is one
of a series of dialogues between Krishnamurti
and Dr. Alan W. Anderson, who
is professor of religious studies at San
Diego State University where he teaches
Indian and Chinese scriptures and the
oracular tradition. Dr. Anderson, a
published poet, received his degree from
Columbia University and the Union
Theological Seminary. He has been honored
with a Distinguished Teaching Award
from the California State Universities.
Mr. Krishnamurti, if I recall correctly, I
think we had begun to talk together
before, last time, just at the point where
the question of fear arose. And I think we
both perhaps could explore that together a little.
Yes, I think so too.
I wonder how we can approach this problem,
because this is a common problem in the world.
Everyone, or I can say
almost everyone, is frightened of something.
Oh, it may be the fear of death, fear of
loneliness, fear of not being loved, fear of not becoming
famous, successful, or also fear of not having
physical security. And I think we can explore
fear of not having physical security, and
the fear of not having psychological security.
There are so many multiple forms of fears.
Now, to go into this problem really very deeply,
can the mind, and which includes the
brain, be really, fundamentally be free of fear?
Because fear, as I have observed, is a dreadful thing.
Oh yes.
It darkens the world, it destroys everything. And
I don't think we can discuss fear, which
is one of the principles in life,
without also discussing or going into the pursuit
of pleasure. The two are the
sides, two sides of the same coin.
Fear and pleasure, two sides of the same coin.
So as we are going to first take
fear, there is conscious as well as unconscious fears,
fears that are observable, that can be remedied,
and fears that are deep rooted, deep in the
recesses of one's mind.
At the unconscious level.
At the deeper levels.
Yes.
Now, we must be concerned with both, not
only the obvious external fears, but also the deep
seated, undiscovered fears. The fears that
have been handed down, traditional fears.
Being told what to fear.
And also fears that the
mind itself has produced, has cultivated.
In one's personal history.
In personal, and also in relation to others.
Yes.
Fears of physical insecurity, losing a job,
losing a position, losing something, and not
or the positive is not having
something, and so on and on.
So if we are going to talk about this
question, how shall we, you and I, approach this? First
the outer, the obvious physical fears, and
then from there move to the inner.
And so cover the whole field, not just one little
fear of an old lady or an old man or
a young man.
You take the whole problem of fear.
Good.
Not just take one leaf of fear, or one
branch of it, but the whole movement of fear.
Yes.
We are back to that word movement again.
Yes, movement of fear.
Good, good.
The whole movement of fear.
Now outwardly, physically, it is becoming
obvious that we must have security. Physical
security, that is food, clothes, and shelter,
are absolutely necessary. Not only for the
Americans, for the whole humanity.
Yes, of course.
And it is no good saying we are secure and
to hell with the rest of the world. The world
is you. And you are the world. You can't
isolate yourself and say, I am going to be
secure and not bother about the others.
Secure myself against them.
Then it becomes a division, conflict, war,
all that produces them. So that physical security
for the brain. The brain can only function,
as I have observed it in myself, in others,
not that I am an expert on brain or
neurology and all that, but I have observed it. The
brain can function only in complete
security. Then it functions efficiently, healthily,
not neurotically, and its actions won't
be lopsided, disheartened. The brain needs
security, as the child needs security. Now,
that security is denied when we separate ourselves.
the Americans, the Russians, the Indians,
the Chinese, the national division has destroyed
that security. Because of wars.
Yes, that is a physical barrier.
Physical fact.
Yes, yes.
And yet we don't see that. Sovereign governments
with their armies, with their navies and all
the rest of it, is destroying security.
In the name of...
In the name of whatever.
Providing it.
Yes.
So, you see, what we are trying to get
at is how stupid the mind is. It wants security
and it must have security, and yet
it is doing everything to destroy that security.
Oh yes, yes, yes, I see that.
So, that is one factor. And the factor
of security is in jobs, either in a factory,
or as a priest in his
job. So, occupation becomes very important.
Indeed it does.
So, see what is involved. If I lose my
job, I am frightened. And that job depends on the
environment, on the production, business,
factory, all that commercialism, consumerism,
and therefore competition with other countries.
France isolating itself because it wants to
which is happening.
Yes.
So, we need physical security and we are doing
everything to destroy it. If we all of us
said, look, let's all get together, not with
plans, not my plan, your plan, or the communist
plan, or Mao's plan, let's as human
beings sit together and solve this problem. They
could do it. Science has the means of
feeding people, but they won't because they are
conditioned to function so as to destroy security
which they are seeking. So, that is one of
the major factors in physical security. Then
there is the fear of physical pain. Physical
in the sense one has had pain, let's say,
last week. Mind is afraid that it should happen
again. So, there is that kind of fear.
It's very interesting with respect to the
phenomenon of physical pain because what is
remembered is not the neurological reaction
but the emotion that attends what occurred.
That's it. So, there is that fear. Then
there is the fear of outward opinion, what people
say, public opinion.
Reputation.
Reputation. You see, sir, all
this is born out of disorder.
I don't know if I...
Oh, yes.
Which we discussed previously.
Yes, which we looked into previously.
So, can the mind bring about security,
physical security, which means food, clothes and shelter
for everybody, not as a communist, as a capitalist,
as a socialist, or as a Mao, but meet together
as human beings to resolve this problem? It can
be done, but nobody wants to do it because
they don't feel responsible for this. I don't know
if you have been to India, if you have
gone from town to town to village, as I
have done, you see the appalling poverty, the degradation
of poverty, the sense of hopelessness of it.
Yes, yes, I have been to India and it was
the first time in my life that I sensed poverty
not simply as a privation but it seemed
to have a positive character about it. It was
so stark.
I know, sir, I know. Personally
we have been through all that.
Oh, yes.
So, physical survival is only possible when
human beings get together, not as communist,
socialist, all the rest, as human beings who
say, look, this is our problem, for God's
sake, let's solve it. But they won't
because they are burdened with problems, with planning.
How to solve that? I don't know if you understand.
Yes, yes, yes, yes.
You have your plan, I have my plan,
he has his plan. So planning becomes most important,
plans become most important rather than the
starvation. And we fight each other. And common
sense, affection, care, love, control, change all this.
So I won't go into that. Then the
fear of public opinion. You
understand? What my neighbour will say.
My image, the national image, yes.
And I depend on my neighbour.
Oh, yes.
If I am a Catholic living in Italy, I
have to depend on my neighbour because I will lose
my job if I am a Protestant then. So I
accept it. I go and salute the Pope or whatever. It
has no meaning. So I am afraid of public
opinion. See what a human mind has reduced itself to.
I don't say to please us with public
opinion because they are stupid. They are conditioned,
as much as I am. So there is that
fear. And there is the fear, physical fear of death,
which is an immense fear. That fear one
has to tackle differently when we come to it,
when we talk about death and all that. So
there is the outward form of fear, fear of
darkness, fear of public opinion, fear of
losing a job, fear of survival, not being
able to survive. Sir, I have lived with people with
one meal a day and that is not enough even.
I have walked behind a woman with a girl
and the girl said in India, mother I am hungry.
And the mother says, you have already
eaten for the day. You understand, sir?
Yes.
So there are all that physical fears, pain
and the fear of recurring pain and that. And
there is the other fears are much more
complicated. Fears of dependency inwardly. I depend on
my wife, I depend on my guru, I depend on
the priest, I depend on so many dependents. And I am
afraid to lose them, to be left alone. To
be rejected. To be rejected. If that woman turns away
from me, I am lost. I get angry, brutal,
violent, jealous, because I have depended on her. So
dependency is one of the factors of fear. And
inwardly I am afraid. I am afraid of loneliness.
The other day I saw on the television a woman
saying, the only fear I have in life is my loneliness.
And therefore being afraid of loneliness I
do all kinds of neurotic activities. Being lonely,
I attach myself to you, or to a belief, or
to a saviour, to a guru, and I protect the guru,
the saviour, the belief, and that soon becomes neurotic.
A. I fill up the hole with this new image.
K. With this rubbish.
A. Yes.
K. There is that fear. Then there is the fear
of not being able to arrive, succeed, succeed in this
world of disorder, and succeed in the
world of spiritual, so-called spiritual world. That's
what they are all doing now.
A. Spiritual achievement.
K. Achievement. Which they call enlightenment.
A. Expanding consciousness.
K. Yes.
A. I know what you mean. It's very interesting
that you just got through describing fear of being
left behind. Now we are
fearing that we will never arrive.
K. All right.
A. Yes. Please go on.
K. Same thing. Then there is the fear
of not being, which translates itself in identification
with. I must identify myself.
A. In order to be.
K. To be. Let me identify myself with my country.
And I say to myself, that's too stupid. Then I
say I must identify myself with God, which I
have invented. God has not made man in his image.
Man has made God in his image.
A. Yes. Oh, I follow you.
そう
Not being, not achieving, not arriving
brings about tremendous sense of uncertainty,
tremendous sense of not being able to fulfil,
not being able to be with.
And the cry, I must be myself.
A. Do my own thing. K.
My own thing, which is rubbish.
So, there are all these fears,
both logical fears, irrational fears, neurotic fears,
and fears of survival, physical survival.
So, now, how do you deal with all these fears,
and many more fears which you can't go into,
which we will presently.
How do you deal with them all, one by one?
A. Well, you would just be
in the mournful round of fragmentation
if you did that.
K. And also there is the fear, hidden fears,
which are much more active.
A. The continual bubbling up from below.
K. When I am not conscious they take over.
A. That's right.
So, how am I to deal, first,
with the obvious fears which we have described,
shall I deal it one by one, first secure myself?
You follow? Or take loneliness and tackle that,
come to grips with it,
go beyond it, and so on?
Or is there a way of dealing with fear,
not with the branches of it,
but with the root of it?
Because if I take each leaf, each branch,
it will take all my lifetime.
And if I begin to analyse my fears, analyse,
then that very analysis becomes a paralysis.
And then I even fear that
I might not have analysed correctly.
K. Correct. And I am caught over and over again.
So how shall I deal with this problem,
as a whole, not just
parts of it, fragments of it?
A. Isn't there a hint about
how it might be dealt with?
Of course, when I say hint
here, I mean terribly, terribly slight.
I don't think I would call it a pointer.
But fear, no matter how
many varieties one imagines he knows,
fear does have a common taste, you might say.
There is something there.
K. Yes, sir, but what shall I do with it?
A. Oh yes, of course, I quite understand.
But it interested me while you were speaking,
to observe that already when we think of many fears,
we haven't even paid attention to
how we fear, when we fear.
Yes, I was interested to have that flash,
because it seems to be altogether consonant
with what you're talking about.
And I said to myself, now, in our conversations
we've been pointing to movement.
The movement of fear is one.
K. Yes, a tremendous one.
A. And it is a unified field of destruction.
K. It is the common factor of every human being.
A. The whole thing, yes, exactly.
K. Whether a man lives in Moscow
or in India or in any place,
it is the common thing of this fear.
And how shall he deal with it?
Because unless the mind is free of fear,
really, not verbally or ideologically,
absolutely be free of fear,
and it is possible to be free, completely of fear.
I'm saying this not as a theory,
but I know what I have gone into very deeply.
A. Actual. K. Actual.
Now, how shall I deal with this?
So I ask myself, what is fear?
Not the objects of fear or the expressions of fear.
A. No, or the instant reaction to danger.
K. Danger. What is fear?
A. It's an idea in my mind in part.
K. What is fear, sir?
A. If we have said it's an abiding...
K. No, behind the words, behind the description,
the explanations, the way out and the way in,
and all the rest of it, what is fear?
How does it come?
A. If I followed you
through our conversations up until now,
I'd be inclined to say that it is another expression
of the observer's disordered relation to the observer.
K. What does that mean? What is the observer?
What you say... Look, the problem is this.
I'm only making the problem clearer so that we can...
We have... Man has tried to lop off or prune
one fear after the other, through analysis, through escape,
through identifying himself with something
which he calls courage, or saying,
I don't care, I rationalise my fears
and remain in a state of rationalised, intellectual,
verbal explanation, but the thing is boiling.
So what shall I do?
What is fear?
Unless I find this out, not because you tell me,
unless I find it out for myself,
as I find for myself that I am hungry.
Nobody has to tell me I'm hungry.
I have to find this out.
A. Yes, now there's a difference here
in terms of what you have just said,
and in so saying, pointing to something.
And my earlier reply, when
you asked me what is fear,
I did the usual academic thing.
If I have followed you up until now,
then it seems clear that...
Whereas, let's forget about the following,
let's zero in on it right now,
and then I must say, not I might say,
but I must say that I can't tell anybody else
what fear is with respect to what it is
I am going to discover in me as such,
and all my continual descriptions about it
are simply a deflection from my immediate issue,
which is here.
Yes. So, I am not escaping.
A. No.
K. I am not rationalising.
I am not analysing, because analysis is real paralysis.
A. Yes, indeed.
K. When you are confronted with a problem like this,
merely spinning over and on analysing,
and the fear of not being able to analyse perfectly,
and therefore go to a
professional who needs also an analysis.
So I am caught. So I will not analyse,
because I see the absurdity of it.
You follow, sir? A. Yes, I do.
K. I won't run.
A. No backing off, no flight.
K. No explanations, no rationalisation, no analysis.
I am faced with this thing.
And what is fear?
Wait a minute. Leave that for the moment.
Then there are the unconscious fears,
of which I don't know.
They express themselves occasionally when I am alert,
when I see this thing coming out of me.
A. When I am alert.
K. Alert. When I am watching.
Or when I am looking
at something, this comes up, uninvited.
Now, it is important for the
mind to be completely free of fear.
It is essential, as food is essential.
It is essential for the
mind to be free of fear.
So I see outwardly what we have discussed,
now I say, what are the hidden fears?
Can I consciously invite them to come to the surface?
You follow? A. Yes, I do.
K. Or the unconscious cannot touch that.
K. Conscious can only deal with the things it knows,
but it cannot observe the thing it doesn't know.
A. Or have access to.
K. So, what am I to do? Dreams?
Dreams are merely a continuation of
what I have lived during the day.
They continue in a different form.
We won't go into that for the moment.
So how is all that to be awakened and exposed?
The racial fears, the fears that society has taught me,
the fears that the family has imposed,
the neighbour, all those crawling,
ugly, brutal things that are hidden,
how shall they all come up naturally
and expose so that the mind sees them completely?
You understand? A. Yes, I do.
I was just thinking about what we are doing
in relation to what you are saying.
Here we are in a university situation
where hardly any listening goes
on at all, if any. Why?
Well, if we were to relate to each other
in terms of my sitting back here,
saying to myself every time you made a statement,
well, what do I have to say back?
Even if my reaction were benign,
and I'd say to myself as a professor,
I'd say, well, now, that's a very interesting concept.
Perhaps we could clear that
up a little bit, you know?
That nonsense.
Nonsense in terms of what is immediate here.
That's what I mean.
I don't mean demonstrating something on the board.
We should never have begun to be together.
Never have started.
And yet we might have given ourselves the idea
that we were trying very hard to be sincere.
Yes, I understand.
But fear is at the base of that too,
because the professor is thinking to himself,
he's got his reputation at stake here,
he better not keep quiet too long
because someone might get the idea
that either he doesn't understand the thing that's going on,
or he doesn't have anything
to contribute to what's going on,
all of which has nothing to do with anything.
K. Absolutely.
So, look, sir, what I have found.
I cannot... the conscious mind, conscious thought,
cannot invite and expose the hidden fears.
It cannot analyse it,
because that analysis we said is inaction.
And if there is no escape,
I shan't run off to a
church, or Jesus, or Buddha, or somebody,
or identify myself with some other thing,
I've pushed all those aside
because I've understood their futility.
So I'm left with this.
I'm this, my baby.
A. Yes. Right.
K. So, what shall I do?
Some action has to take place.
A. Yes, indeed.
K. I can't just say,
well, I've pushed all that aside,
I'll just sit.
Now, just see what happens, sir.
Because I've pushed all those aside,
through observation, not through
resistance, not through violence,
because I've negated all those
– escape, analysis, running off to something,
and all the rest of that –
I have energy, haven't I?
The mind has energy now.
A. Now it has, yes. Yes, it flugs up.
K. Because I've pushed away
all the things that dissipate energy.
A. Energy leaks.
K. Therefore I have now this thing.
I'm confronted with that, confronted with fear.
Now, what can I do?
Listen to this, sir. What can I do?
I can't do anything.
Because it is I who have created the fear.
Public opinion.
A. Yes, yes, yes.
K. Right? So I cannot do a thing about fear.
A. Precisely.
K. But there is the energy which has been gathered,
which has come into being when
all dissipation of energy has ended.
There's energy.
You follow?
A. Exactly, virtue. Right, right. Manifested.
K. Energy. Now, what happens?
This is not some hocus-pocus.
This is some kind of mystical experience.
There is actual fear and I have tremendous energy
which has come because there is no dissipation of energy.
So what takes place?
So wait, wait, wait, wait.
A. Oh, I'm waiting. I'm waiting.
K. Wait, wait.
A. I was just... there
was something going through my mind.
K. Yes. What takes place?
So I say, so what has created fear?
What has brought it about?
Because if I have the energy, you follow, sir,
to put that question and
find the answer for that question.
I've got energy now. I don't know...
A. Yes, yes, yes.
K. So what has brought it about?
You, my neighbour, my country, my culture?
A. Myself.
K. What has brought it about?
A. I've done it.
K. Who is I?
A. I don't mean I as
the fragmented observer of for me.
It is this...
I'm thinking what you said
earlier about the mind as disordered,
which requires to empty itself of the disorder.
Doesn't require another mind to do it.
K. I'm asking, what has brought this fear into me,
into my consciousness?
I won't use that word because
we'll have to go into it.
We'll have to go into that in a different way.
What has brought this fear?
And I won't leave it till
I find it. You understand, sir?
Because I've got the energy to do it.
I don't depend on anybody, on
any book, on any philosopher, nobody.
A. Would it be the case
that once that energy begins to flood
that the question itself disappears?
K. And I begin to find the answer.
A. Yes.
K. I don't put the
question, but I find the answer.
A. Right, right.
K. Now, what is the answer?
A. The answer couldn't be...
K. Academic.
A. Academic, a description or something.
A change has occurred in the being.
K. What is the answer to this fact of fear
which has been sustained, which has been nourished,
which has carried on from generation to generation?
So, I must...
Can the mind observe this fear, the movement of it?
Not just a piece of fear.
A. Or a succession of fears.
K. But the movement of this whole movement of fear.
Observe it without the thought
that has created the observer.
Right?
A. Oh, yes, yes, yes.
K. So, can there be observation of this fact,
which I have called it fear?
Because I have recognised it, the mind has recognised it,
because it has had fear before.
So, through recognition and association,
it says this is fear.
A. Yes, and that never stops.
K. Wait. So, can the mind observe without the observer,
who is the thinker, observe this fact only?
That means, can the observer, which is thought,
the observer, as thought, has produced this?
I don't know. So, thought has produced this.
Right? I am afraid of my neighbour.
What he says, because I want to be respectable.
That is the product of thought.
Thought has divided the world into America, Russia,
India, China, and all the rest of it,
and that destroys security. That is the result of thought.
I am lonely, and therefore I act neurotically.
Which is also the fact of thought.
So, I see very clearly
that thought is responsible for that.
Right? Right, sir? So, what will happen with thought then?
Thought is responsible for this.
It has nourished it, it has sustained it,
it has encouraged it, it
has done everything to sustain it.
I am afraid of the pain that I had yesterday
happening again tomorrow, which is the movement of thought.
So, can thought, which can only
function within the field of knowledge,
that is its ground.
And fear is something new each time.
Fear isn't old. It is
made old when I recognise it.
But when the process of recognition,
which is the association of words and so on,
can the mind observe that
without the interference of thought?
If it does, fear is not.
A. Right. The thing that was hitting
me while I was sitting here intently,
the thing that was hitting me
was that the moment that occurs,
the thought and the fear immediately disappear.
K. So, fear then can be put away completely.
If I was living as a human being in Russia,
and they threatened me to put
into prison, probably you would be afraid.
It is a natural self-preservation.
A. Of course.
K. That is a natural fear,
like a bus coming rushing towards you,
you step aside, you run away from a dangerous animal.
That is a natural self-protective reaction.
But that is not fear.
It is a response of intelligence operating,
saying, for God's sake, move away from the rushing bus.
But the other factors are factors of thought.
A. Exactly.
K. So, can thought understand itself and
know its place and not project itself?
Not control, which is an abomination.
If you control thought, who is the controller?
Another fragment of thought.
A. Not the thought.
K. It is a vicious
game you are playing with yourself.
So, can the mind observe without a movement of thought?
It will only do that when you
have understood the whole movement of thought.
have understood the whole movement of fear.
Understood that, not analysed, looking at it.
It is a living thing, therefore
you have to look at it.
It is only a dead thing that
can dissect and analyse, kick it around.
But a living thing you have to watch.
Like it will...
A. This is very shocking, because in our last conversation,
just towards the end, we came to
the place where we raised the question of
someone saying to himself, I think
I understand what I have heard.
Now I am going to try that.
And then fear holds up a mirror to itself.
K. Of course.
A. And one is suddenly ringed
about by a world of mirrors.
K. You don't say, sir, when you
see a dangerous animal, I think about it.
You move, you act, because
there is tremendous destruction waiting there.
There is a self-protective reaction,
which is intelligence, get out.
Here we are not using intelligence.
And intelligence operates when we
have looked at all these fears,
the movements of it, the inwardness of
it, the subtlety of it, the whole movement.
Then out of that comes intelligence
and says, I have understood it.
A. It is marvellous. Yes, it is very beautiful.
Very beautiful.
We were going to say something about pleasure.
K. Ah, that must be dealt.
A. We will write, exactly.
K. So, sir, look, we said
there is physical fears and psychological fears.
A. Yes.
K. Both are interrelated.
You can't say, well, that's one, this is the other.
They are all interrelated.
And the interrelationship and
the understanding of that relationship
brings this intelligence which will operate physically,
saying, let us then work
together, co-operate together to feed man.
You follow, sir?
Let's not be national, religious, sectarian.
What is important? To feed man, to
clothe him, to make him live happily.
But you see, unfortunately, we are
so disorderly in our ways of life
that we have no time for anything else.
Our disorder is consuming us.
A. It's interesting in relation to tradition.
I don't mean to start an entirely new conversation now,
but just to see what is immediately suggested,
among many other things that
would be, but just this one.
What we could say about the interrelationship
and what we could say about the misuses of tradition
would be that we are actually taught what to fear.
K. Yes, that's absolutely true.
A. In our language we have an expression, don't we,
that expresses part of this old wives' tales, we say.
An accumulation of warnings about things
that are simply imaginary.
Not in the creative sense of imagination,
and I'm using the word creative there very loosely,
but fantasia, phantasmagoria,
from the little one's earliest years
gets this stuff with the bottle.
K. And then when we get into adolescence,
we reflect on these things we've learned,
and if things go wrong we feel that perhaps
it's because we haven't sufficiently
grasped what we've been told.
And then some young people will say it,
but I'm adjunct the whole thing,
but then immediately the loneliness question arises.
K. They can't... Sir, it is life, this is life.
You can't reject one part
when you accept the other part.
A. Exactly.
K. Life means all this.
Freedom, order, disorder,
communication, relationship, response,
it's the whole thing is living.
If we don't understand simply,
I don't want to have anything to do with it,
you're not living, you're dying.
A. Yes, of course.
I wonder...
I wonder how much...
I wonder... I keep saying I wonder,
and the reason I wonder is because
what we have been saying about this movement
as a unified field is when stated,
taken by thought,
and you might say put in the refrigerator, and
that's the reality to the person.
K. Right, sir.
And when we want to look at
it, well, it's one of the ice cubes,
we break out and have a look.
A. That's right, sir.
What place has knowledge in the regeneration of man?
Look, our knowledge is you must be separate.
You are an American, I'm a Hindu, that's our knowledge.
Our knowledge is you must rely on your neighbour
because he knows he's respectable.
Society is respectability, society is
moral, so you accept that.
So knowledge has brought about all these factors.
And you are telling me suddenly,
asking me what place has that?
What place has tradition?
What place has the accumulated knowledge of millennia,
the accumulated knowledge of science,
mathematics, and that is essential.
But what place has knowledge,
which I have gathered through experience,
through generations after generation of human endeavour,
what place has it in the transformation of fear?
None whatsoever. You see.
No, clear, clear.
Because what we reached before, that
upon the instant that this is grasped,
the thought that was operating as
a fragment and the fear vanish.
And it isn't that something takes its place in succession.
No, nothing takes its place.
Nothing takes its place.
It doesn't mean there is emptiness.
Oh, no, no, no, no,
no, no, no, no, no, no.
But you see, it's right there.
When you start thinking about that
as a thought, you get scared.
That's why it's very important
to find out or to understand
the function of knowledge
and where knowledge becomes ignorance.
We mix the two together.
Knowledge is essential to English,
speaking English, driving a dozen,
knowledge is essential.
But when that knowledge becomes ignorance,
when we are trying to understand actually what is,
the what is, is this
fear, this disorder, this irresponsibility.
To understand it, you don't have to have knowledge.
All that you have to do is to look.
Look outside you, look inside you,
and then you see clearly
that knowledge is absolutely unnecessary,
it has no value in the
transformation or the regeneration of man.
Because freedom is not born of knowledge.
Freedom is when all the burdens are not.
You don't have to search for freedom.
It comes when the other is not.
It isn't something in place of
the horror that was there before.
Yes, yes.
I think that's enough.
Yes, yes, I quite follow you.
Maybe next time we could...
Tomorrow we can carry on.
We could carry on into this...
With pleasure and so on.
With pleasure as such, the opposite side of that coin.